A Guide to the Austin Kennell Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10553-z
Austin Kennell Papers ca. 1952-1993
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10553-z
ca. 7000 items
Austin Kennell
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Austin Kennell, Waynesboro, Virginia, on September 17, 1993.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of the American Rhododendron Society, ca. 7,000 items (16 Hollinger boxes, 6 linear shelf feet), ca. 1952, and 1967-1993, consists of correspondence, topical files, committee files, memoranda, meeting minutes, activities files, and membership lists, all pertaining to the rhododendron interests and organizational involvement of Austin Kennell of Waynesboro, Virginia, as Director, President (1989-1991), and Vice-President of the American Rhododendron Society and President of the Middle Atlantic Chapter.
Kennell's personal correspondence (first series, boxes 1-4) includes files on several well-known rhododendron enthusiasts and nurseries (for a complete list of correspondents see the box listing on pages 3-5). The second series (boxes 5-12) contains files pertaining to his work with the national organization, the American Rhododendron Society, with the bulk of the files containing the minutes of the meetings of the Board of Directors; Conventions; correspondence with the executive secretary, Paula Cash, other officers, and the registrar; and a special subseries concerning the various committees of the organization.
The last series (boxes 13-16) is concerned with his involvement in the Middle Atlantic Chapter of the American Rhododendron Society, and includes correspondence with William F. Bedwell, Paul S. James, Sandra and Kenneth McDonald, Pete and Terry Sheuchenko, and Harry L. Wise; and minutes for the meetings of the Chapter and its Board of Directors.
Austin Kennell was born in Cumberland, Maryland, on January 22, 1918, graduating from Cumberland High School in 1936. He served in the Navy 1943-1945 and 1951-1952, having married in 1940. Kennell held various industrial and governmental positions in Maryland and Washington, DC before moving to the Waynesboro area where he served as an executive with the Virginia Metalcrafters. Altogether Kennell worked for Virginia Metalcrafters for twenty-four years before retiring in 1984. Kennell has also operated a family mail-order business, Dandy Sales, Inc., selling parts for special lines of obsolete lawn mowers and garden tractors since 1973.
Austin Kennell was a member of the American Rhododendron Society Board of Directors for ten years and had served as eastern vice-president and senior vice-president prior to his election as president in 1989. He also served as the chairman who directed all activities for the first American Rhododendron Society convention held in Virginia at Williamsburg in 1988.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence Files
  - Correspondence: Nick& Neala Anastos, 1984-1989 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: T. Coleman Andrews, 1970 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Jim Barlup, 1980-1985 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Basket Neck Nursery, 1977-1983 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Edward A. Cary, 1974-1983 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: L. C. Case, 1978-1983 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Richard P. Clark, 1972-1987 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Fred D. Conant, 1980-1982 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Earl Cordy, 1980-1983 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Sidney& Grace Deibert, 1976-1987 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Dexter Study Group, 1980-1983 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Ellanhurst Gardens, 1984-1988 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Jim Elliott, 1975-1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Exports, 1974-1977 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Exbury Gardens, 1974-1975 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Kathleen B. Frederick, 1977-1978 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Girard Nurseries, 1978-1991 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Gladsgay Gardens Nursery, 1975-1977 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: David W. Goheen, 1975-1977 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Gordner's Rhododendron Nursery, Inc., 1982-1986 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Gossler Farms Nursery, 1982-1987 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Greer Gardens, 1972-1975 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: George W. Harding, 1976-1984 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Allen Harris, 1972-1976 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Hydon Nurseries Ltd., 1975-1980 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Don Kellam, 1976-1983 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Kingsville Nurseries, 1968-1977 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence: John G. Lofthouse, 1972-1983 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Thomas J. McGuire, 1974-1976 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Cliff Mashburn, 1980-1985 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: George Miller, 1975-1983 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous, 1972-1985 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Guy G. Nearing, 1968-1977 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Carl H. Phetteplace, 1975-1982; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Rainer Mt. Alpine Gardens, 1973-1975 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Alfred A. Raustein, 1975-1985 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Redbarn Nursery, 1968-1980 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: G. Albert Reid, 1981-1982 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: S. D. Coleman Nurseries, 1971-1980 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Henry T. Skinner, 1971-1984 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Albert W. Smith, 1987-1989 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Clint Smith, 1985-1990 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence: David Smith, 1983 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Van Veen Nursery, 1982-1988 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Wells Nursery, 1971-1972 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Weston Nurseries, Inc., 1977-1990 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Winterset Nursery, 1987-1992 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Douglas Dell Withers, 1967-1979; (3 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Wynterset Nurseries, Inc., 1984-1985 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Henry and Maletta Yates, 1969-1989 (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Zolling Rhododendron Specialty Nursery, 1969-1973 (Box Box 4)
- Series II: American Rhododendron Society Papers
  - Subseries A: Correspondence & Topical Files
    - Alderman Library as Repository for the Archives of the American Rhododendron Society, 1983-1990 (Box Box 5)
    - Brochures, ca. 1990 (Box Box 5)
    - Paula Cash- Correspondence, 1985-1990 (Box Box 5)
    - Chapter Presidents List, 1989 (Box Box 5)
    - Conventions, 1976-1992; (4 folders) (Box Box 5)
    - Executive Director/Executive Secretary - Correspondence, 1989-1991; (3 folders) (Box Box 6)
    - Financial Statements, 1981-1990 (Box Box 6)
    - Insurance Information, 1986-1988 (Box Box 6)
    - International Rhododendron Societies - Correspondence & Publications, 1989-1990 (Box Box 6)
    - Journal of the American Rhododendron Society, 1979-1992; (2 folders) (Box Box 6)
    - Journal of the American Rhododendron Society- Index, 1970, 1980 (Box Box 6)
    - Membership Lists, 1982-1992 (Box Box 7)
    - Memoranda to the Board of Directors, 1989-1991 (Box Box 7)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors' Meetings and Related Papers, 1977-1985; (6 folders) (Box Box 7)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors' Meetings and Related Papers, 1986-1990 Jun; (8 folders) (Box Box 8)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors' Meetings and Related Papers, 1990 Jul-1993; (5 folders) (Box Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1984-1990 (Box Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous Other Societies - Information, 1989-1990 (Box Box 9)
    - Newsletters, 1980-1989 (Box Box 9)
    - Officers - Correspondence, ca. 1985-1992; (2 folders) (Box Box 10)
    - Pollen Bank, 1982-1991 (Box Box 10)
    - Registrar - Correspondence, 1986-1991 (Box Box 10)
    - Rhododendron Society of Canada- Possible Affiliation w/ the American Rhododendron Society, 1988-1992 (Box Box 10)
    - Seed Exchange, 1982-1993; (2 folders) (Box Box 10)
    - Slide Library, 1982-1991 (Box Box 10)
    - Western Regional Conference & Board of Directors Meeting Combined Trip, 1990 (Box Box 10)
  - Subseries B: Committees
    - Azalea Committee, 1989-1991 (Box Box 11)
    - Budget & Finance Committee, 1983-1991 (Box Box 11)
    - Bylaws Revision Committee, 1978-1993; (3 folders) (Box Box 11)
    - District Advisory Committee, 1983-1985 (Box Box 11)
    - Editorial Committee, 1984-1991 (Box Box 11)
    - Editor Search Committee, 1990-1991 (Box Box 11)
    - Executive Committee, 1989-1990 (Box Box 11)
    - General Committee Information, 1989-1990 (Box Box 11)
    - Honors Committee, 1984-1991 (Box Box 11)
    - International Rhododendron Union Committee, 1983-1991 (Box Box 11)
    - Long Range Planning Committee, 1984-1991 (Box Box 12)
    - Nominating Committee, 1989-1991 (Box Box 12)
    - Pioneer Award Committee, 1985-1991 (Box Box 12)
    - Plant Awards Committee, 1980-1991 (Box Box 12)
    - Public Relations Committee, 1985-1991 (Box Box 12)
    - Ratings Committee, 1982-1991 (Box Box 12)
    - Research Committee and Foundation, 1982-1991 (Box Box 12)
    - Research Foundation, 1985-1991 (Box Box 12)
    - The Sandwich Club Task Force, 1989-1992 (Box Box 12)
    - Shows & Judging Committee, 1989-1990 (Box Box 12)
    - Speaker's Bureau Committee, 1987-1992 (Box Box 12)
- Series III: Middle Atlantic Chapter Papers
  - Articles and Hand-Outs re Rhododendrons, 1973-1983, n.d. (Box Box 13)
  - Awards and Honors, 1979-1990 (Box Box 13)
  - William F. Bedwell Correspondence, 1981-1989; (3 folders) (Box Box 13)
  - Bylaws, 1952 (Box Box 13)
  - Finance Committee, 1988-1989 (Box Box 13)
  - Paul S. James Correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box Box 13)
  - Lewis Ginter Botanical Garden, ca. 1986-1988 (Box Box 13)
  - Sandra& Kenneth McDonald Correspondence, 1977-1992; (3 folders) (Box Box 13)
  - Meetings of the Middle Atlantic Chapter, 1976-1992; (5 folders) (Box Box 14)
  - Membership & Officer Lists, 1978-1984 (Box Box 14)
  - Minutes of the Board of Directors Meetings and Related Papers, 1980-1982 (Box Box 14)
  - Minutes of the Board of Directors Meetings and Related Papers, 1983-1992; (2 folders) (Box Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous Papers re the Middle Atlantic Chapter, 1977-1993, n.d.; (5 folders) (Box Box 15)
  - Newsletters, 1976-1992; (3 folders) (Box Box 16)
  - Plant Diseases, 1975-1990 (Box Box 16)
  - Pollen Bank, 1979-1980 (Box Box 16)
  - Ratings of "Do-Gooders" Rhododendron, 1979-1985 (Box Box 16)
  - Pete and Terry Sheuchenko Correspondence, 1980-1993 (Box Box 16)
  - Species Study Group, 1982-1983 (Box Box 16)
  - Harry L. Wise Correspondence, 1980-1992 (Box Box 16)